A Guide to the Papers of Joseph L. Vaughan 1931- 1999
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Papers of Joseph L. Vaughan 1931-1999
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
12716-c
The collection contains ca. 265 items (12 Hollinger boxes, 5 linear feet).
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
This collection was given to the Special Collections Department, University of Virginia Library by Ann Vaughan Sahlman (Joseph L. Vaughan's daughter) on July 30, 2004
Biographical/Historical Information
Joseph L. Vaughan was the first Provost for the University of Virginia (1956-1960) under University President Colgate Darden. He was also Chancellor of the University of Virginia Branch Colleges (1960-1966) under President Edgar Shannon. Vaughan was instrumental in upgrading George Mason College to a University and expanding Clinch Valley to a four year college. He was considered to be one of the University's all time great teachers. Of particular note was his ability to teach engineering students the importance of English literature which he passionately believed would give them a broadened perspective as future engineers and in other areas of their lives.
He was born in Lynchburg, Virginia on January 26, 1905. He received all of his degrees from the University of Virginia; B.A. in 1926; MA in 1927; Ph.D. in 1940. He taught courses at the University from 1926 until 1975 when he retired with the rank of Professor Emeritus. He was President of the Raven Society as a student; Rector and Visitors Fellow (1926-27); Head of a newly organized Division of English, School of Engineering (1936-1940); President of the Institute of Textile Technology (1951-1953); Recipient of Harry St. John Dixon Award (1954); Provost (1956-1960); Chancellor for University of Virginia Community Colleges (1960-1966); President Board of Directors of the National Bank & Trust Company (1962); Chair of the Humanities, School of Engineering and Applied Science (1970); Raven Award (1970); Distinguished Professor Award (1971); Mac Wade Award (1975); President of the Phi Beta Kappa Society; Vaughan House was named for him (1992); Fellow of Weedon House New College (1993); Omicron Delta kappa; Pi Delta Epsilon; Significant Sig Award; Industrial consultant to corporations such as Sperry Piedmont Company, Fieldcrest Mills and others; Artist Designation by the Virginia Water Color Society.
Vaughan was the author of the Rotunda Tales, a book that reveals his longtime personal knowledge about the University of Virginia and its professors and presidents. He also wrote Thomas Jefferson's Rotunda Restored, 1973-1976 as well as many journal articles, and other literature and science publications.
Scope and Content
The collection contains ca. 265 items (12 Hollinger boxes, 5 linear feet) including 28 handwritten journals spanning the academic and personal life of former University of Virginia Provost and Professor Emeritus Joseph L.Vaughan from 1931 to 1999 (two weeks prior to his death at age 93). In the journals are his descriptions of colleagues; university events; program guides; personal reflections on his family, religion and views on his life's work. There is also one art journal containing his sketches and an address book.
The rest of the collection consists of an assortment of items relating to his work and family life such as: Artistic work by Vaughan including an article in the Albemarle Magazine (June 7, 1997), and the University of Virginia Alumni News (July 1993) as well as photographs of his paintings. Awards information consists of a letter from the Seven Society saluting Vaughan for his 48 years of service to the University of Virginia; a letter from John E. Gibson nominating Vaughan for the recognition for his service; a letter from Vaughan's daughter Ann V. Sahlman describing a gift from the University to Vaughan upon his retirement (a lap desk replication of the one that Thomas Jefferson used while writing the Declaration of Independence. It was also made from wood found in the original Rotunda walls that were removed during restoration. The replicated lap desk is now being used at Monticello.) There is also a note describing a Rotunda Rosette as a gift to Vaughan and the actual Rosette. The collection also contains biographical information; a copyright for the Rotunda Tales; an article in Alumni News about the Rotunda Tales; correspondence between Vaughan and his wife that began when they first met and continued for the rest of their lives; family photographs; and a genealogy including a CD of the family tree.
There is also historical information on the University of Virginia Engineering School's Humanities Department; a copy of Vaughan's remarks on the Honor System from a publication celebrating its 150 years; Institute of Textile Technology brochures and a Daily Progress Lifestyle article about Vaughan's commitment to ITT; negatives of family photographs from 1930 to 1952. There are newspaper clippings about him as the first provost of the University of Virginia, as Chancellor of the University's Branch Colleges, his Phi Beta Kappa associations and his work at the Institute of Textile Technology. Other newspaper articles are about University Presidents Darden and Shannon. There are copies of the obituaries for Joseph L. Vaughan in many newspapers including the Richmond Times Dispatch, Charlottesville Daily Progress, Cavalier Daily, and Inside UVA. There is also an article by Susan Tyler Hitchcock and a Bryan McKenzie editorial column written at the time of Vaughan's death. There is an e-mail from the Dean of the Engineering School, Richard Miksad as well as a copy of his death certificate and an obituary for Ann Doner Vaughan. There is also an audiocassette recording of Vaughan's funeral service; slides of the University of Virginia taken by Vaughan; a speech that Vaughan gave titled "Thomas Jefferson's Answer To Old Age" at a conference on the Role of Aging in the Field of Education and photographs of himself in his office, and with his colleagues. Other photographs are of the National Bank and Trust Board ,The Lawn, The Chapel, Vaughan teaching classes, Ralph Cherry, Bob Gooch, John Barbour, Doc and Frances Ballou, Jane and Joe McGeehan; photographs of the Vaughan House that was named for him in 1994; photographs of family vacations. Miscellaneous items: Coal Miner's bracelet; poem by his wife Ann Doner Vaughan, a letter about the loss of their family dog, and an undated poem by Vaughan.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged in two series, the papers of Joseph L. Vaughan and then his journals. The papers are organized alphabetically by topic and chronologically within each folder.
Contents List
- Artistic work by Vaughan 1993 (Box-folder 1:1)
- Awards 1975;1990;2004 (Box-folder 1:2)
- Biographical information on Vaughan 1993 (Box-folder 1:3)
- Copyright for Rotunda Tales 1984 (Box-folder 1:4)
- Correspondence between Joe and Ann Vaughan 1929-1990 (Box-folder 1:5)
- Vaughan family photographs 1906-1988 (Box-folder 1:6)
- Vaughan genealogy 1864-2004 (Box-folder 1:7)
- Historical information on the Humanites Department 1983 (Box-folder 1:8)
- Honor 150 1992 (Box-folder 1:9)
- Institute of Textile Technology 1994;n.d. (Box-folder 1:10)
- Miscellaneous 1996 (Box-folder 1:11)
- Negatives of family photographs 1930-1946 (Box-folder 1:12)
- Newspaper clippings 1956-1960 (Box-folder 1:13)
- Obituaries of Joe Vaughan 1991;1999 (Box-folder 1:14)
- Slides of the University of Virginia 1960-1961;1975-1976 (Box-folder 1:15)
- Speech written by Vaughan 1961 (Box-folder 1:16)
- Photographs from University of Virginia Career 1939-1973 (Box-folder 1:17)
- Photographs of the Vaughan House 1994 (Box-folder 1:18)
- Family vacations 1994;n.d. (Box-folder 1:19)
- Journals
  - Journal of Joseph L. Vaughan 1931 July 13-1935 Dec 13 (Box-folder 2:1)
  - Journal of Joseph L. Vaughan 1935 Jan 3 - 1938 Jan 23 (Box-folder 2:2)
  - Journal of Joseph L. Vaughan 1938 Feb 8-Sept 17 (Box-folder 2:3)
  - Journal of Joseph L. Vaughan 1938 Oct 31-1939 Dec 27 (Box-folder 2:4)
  - Journal of Joseph L. Vaughan 1939 Dec 31-1941 Jan 5 (Box-folder 2:5)
  - Journal of Joseph L. Vaughan 1941 Jan 26-Dec 30 (Box-folder 2:6)
  - Journal of Joseph L. Vaughan 1942 Jan 11-1943 Jun 21 (Box-folder 3:1)
  - Journal of Joseph L. Vaughan 1943 Jun 23-1945 Sept 28 (Box-folder 3:2)
  - Journal of Joseph L. Vaughan 1945 Sept 29-1947 Feb 23 (Box-folder 3:3)
  - Journal of Joseph L. Vaughan 1947 Feb 24-1949 Feb 20 (Box-folder 3:4)
  - Journal of Joseph L. Vaughan 1949 Feb 22-1952 Sept 29 (Box-folder 4:1)
  - Journal of Joseph L. Vaughan 1952 Oct 1-1955 Jul 31 (Box-folder 4:2)
  - Journal of Joseph L. Vaughan 1955 Aug 2-1957 Dec 31 (Box-folder 5:1)
  - Journal of Joseph L. Vaughan 1958 Jan 1-1959 Apr 29 (Box-folder 5:2)
  - Journal of Joseph L. Vaughan 1959 Apr 30-1960 Mar 30 (Box-folder 5:3)
  - Journal of Joseph L. Vaughan 1960 Mar 31-Dec 31 (Box-folder 6:1)
  - Journal of Joseph L. Vaughan 1960 Jun 7-Aug 3 Europe (Box-folder 6:2)
  - Journal of Joseph L. Vaughan 1961 Jan 1-Dec 30 (Box-folder 6:3)
  - Journal of Joseph L. Vaughan 1962 Jan 1-1963 Aug 1 (Box-folder 6:4)
  - Journal of Joseph L. Vaughan 1963 Aug 1-1965 Apr 30 (Box-folder 7:1)
  - Journal of Joseph L. Vaughan 1965 May 1-1966 Dec 31 (Box-folder 7:2)
  - Journal of Joseph L. Vaughan 1967 Jan 1-1969 Sept 30 (Box-folder 7:3)
  - Journal of Joseph L. Vaughan 1969 Oct 2-1972 Jan 10 (Box-folder 8:1)
  - Journal of Joseph L. Vaughan 1972 Jan 1-1974 Apr 19 (Box-folder 8:2)
  - Journal of Joseph L. Vaughan 1974 Apr 20-1975 Dec 27 (Box-folder 8:3)
  - Journal of Joseph L. Vaughan 1976 Jan 6-1977 July 31 (Box-folder 9:1)
  - Journal of Joseph L. Vaughan 1977 Aug 3-1980 Jan 31 (Box-folder 9:2)
  - Journal of Joseph L. Vaughan 1980 Feb 2-1983 Oct 26 (Box-folder 9:3)
  - Journal of Joseph L. Vaughan 1983 Nov 1-1989 Mar 31 (Box-folder 10:1)
  - Journal of Joseph L. Vaughan 1989 Apr 6; Apr 8 (only two entries) (Box-folder 10:2)
  - Journal of Joseph L. Vaughan 1989 Apr 6-1991 Dec 7 (Box-folder 10:3)
  - Journal of Joseph L. Vaughan 1991 Dec 12-1995 Dec 31 (Box-folder 11:1)
  - Journal of Joseph L. Vaughan 1996 Jan 1-1999 Jan 12 (Box-folder 11:2)
  - Journal of Joseph L. Vaughan Addendum to 1997 Aug 25 entry (Box-folder 11:3)
  - Journal of Joseph L. Vaughan 1960 Oct-1997 Nov (Box-folder 12:1)
  - Address book n.d. (Box-folder 12:2)